Guide to the Dana Gioia Ephemera, 1984-1994
Department of Special Collections
Dana Gioia ephemera,
1984-1994
M0699
Gioia, Dana,
1.5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
American poet, literary critic, and translator.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift of Dana Gioia, 1994.
Biography
Dana Gioia (b. December 24, 1950) is a poet, literary critic, and translator. He was born in Hawthorne, California, the first of his parents' (Michael Gioia and Dorothy Ortiz Gioia) four children. He received his bachelor's degree in English in 1973 from Stanford University. During his undergraduate years, he wrote for and eventually edited Sequoia, the campus literary magazine. After Stanford he earned his masters' degree in English from Harvard University. There, Robert Fitzgerald and Elizabeth Bishop were among his professors. Dissatisfied by the prospect of a career in academia, Gioia left Harvard for Stanford's Business School before he finished his Ph.D. Gioia, then, worked for General Foods from 1977 until 1992 rising to Vice President, all the while continuing to write. Since 1992, he has devoted full time to his literary career. Sometimes referred to as a "New Formalist," Gioia searches in his writing for his own form, assimilating both traditional and free verse forms. Among his collections of poetry are Daily Horoscope (1986), The Gods of Winter (1991), and Planting a Sequoia (1991). He has also published many reviews, essays, and a collection of translations of Eugenia Montale's Italian poems. Gioia's support of and interest in small presses add to his literary reputation and to his visibility as a young poet. He writes frequently for The Hudson Review. He is the President of the Board of Directors of the Story Line Press (successor of The Reaper, Inc. which published the poetry magazine, The Reaper). Gioia also joined the Board of Directors of the Wesleyan University Writers Conference in 1985.
This biography compiled with reference to the Dictionary of Literary Biography. Volume 120. Edited by R. S. Gwynn. 84-90.
Scope and Content
The material in this collection has been sent to William G. McPheron, the Stanford University Libraries' Curator of British and American Literature, by Dana Gioia as a sampling of his published and printed works, beginning in 1986 and continuing through the present.
Gioia's and McPheron's correspondence with the materials Gioia sends mark the increasing visibility and influence of Gioia's literary voice.
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Carlson, Bernice Wells.; Helm, Robert.; Irwin, Virginia.; McPheron, William G.; Aralia Press.; Elizabeth Press.; Greywolf Press.; Story Line Press.; Wesleyan Writers Conference.; Phonotapes.
Collection Contents
- I. Correspondence
  - Dana Gioia to William G. McPheron 7/1986-12/1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Dana Gioia to William G. McPheron 1/1987-7/1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Dana Gioia to William G. McPheron 8/1988-8/1989 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Dana Gioia to William G. McPheron 9/1989-12/1990 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Dana Gioia to William G. McPheron 1/1991-3/1993 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - William G. McPheron to Dana Gioia 7/1986-6/1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - William G. McPheron to Dana Gioia 9/1989-10/1990 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - William G. McPheron to Dana Gioia 9/1991-6/1994 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - William G. McPheron to Bernice Wells Carlson; Dana Gioia to Bernice Wells Carlson (1985-1986) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - William G. McPheron to Robert Helm 1987 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Virginia Irwin to William G. McPheron 1989 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Michael T. Ryan to Dana Gioia 1/30/1989 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- II. Printed Material
  - Broadsides by Dana Gioia (Aralia Press) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Broadsides by Dana Gioia ("The Printed Poem/The Poem as Print") ca.1985 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Reprints from The Hudson Review, by Dana Gioia 1981-1990 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Reprint of "Studying with Miss Bishop" (New Yorker), by Dana Gioia Sept. 15, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Review of Dana Gioia's Daily Horoscope 1987 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Sample Covers for Daily Horoscope and The Gods of Winter (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Ephemera celebrating life of Michael Jasper Gioia 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Mock-up of Poetry Matters, no. 8, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Aralia Press: Bright Dusk, by Daniel Corrie 1990 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Aralia Press: Ephemera 1985-1993 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Elizabeth Press (James L. Weil): (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Keats, John. To My Brother George. 1984
    - Hazlitt, William. On the Living Poets. 1986
    - Shapiro, Karl. On Reading Keats in War Time. 1986
    - Weil, James L. and Jack Hnizdovsky. Two Poems to Two Prints. 1987
    - Shapiro, Karl. The Alphabet. 1988
    - Keats, John. Dear Reynolds, as last night
    - Keats, John. I lay in bed. 1991
  - Elizabeth Press Pamphlets: (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Bronk, William. Formalities. 1990
    - Bronk, William. Formal Declaration. 1990
    - Laughlin, James. Some People Think. 1984
    - Perlman, John. With Sun On. 1985
    - Bronk, William. The Attendant.1984
    - Eigner, Larry. there now here. 1985
    - Bronk, William. The Life. 1986
    - Woodhouse, Richard. Something Given. 1990
    - Bronk, William. Winter Evening. 1986
    - Brown, Spencer. Letter to a Young Poet. n.d.
    - Shapiro, Karl. "A Room in Rome." 1987
    - Bronk, William. The Untold. 1986
    - Bronk, William. Holy Orders. 1986
    - Keats, John. Wise and Otherwise. 1986
    - Bronk, William. Equinox. 1984
    - Bronk, William. What Art Is. 1986
    - Cox, Sidney. On the Lookout for a Poet. 1988
  - Graywolf Press ephemera (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Story Line Press ephemera (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Wesleyan Writers Conference Catalogs 1986-1994 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Announcements re: Gioia n.d. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Announcements re: Gioia 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Announcements re: Gioia 1986 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Announcements re: Gioia 1987 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Announcements re: Gioia 1988 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Announcements re: Gioia 1989 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Announcements re: Gioia 1990 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Announcements re: Gioia 1991 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Announcements re: Gioia 1992 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Announcements re: Gioia1993 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Announcements re: Gioia 1994 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous Reprints (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Collected articles on D. Gioia (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Collected articles on D. Gioia (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Collected articles on D. Gioia (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - "A Garland for John Finlay" 1990, (2 copies) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Poetry Review, v. 81, no. 4. 1991/1992 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Can Poetry Matter?, by Dana Gioia 1992 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - "Un Reservoir à Paysages," by Dana Gioia and Fulvio Testa and "Traveling Images and Observations, Immagini e Annotazioni" by Fulvio Testa, Gioia Timpanelli and Dana Gioia (1987) (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - "Passion: National Juried Visual Art and Poetry Exhibition" (text by Dana Gioia)1994 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - VIA (Voices in Italian Americana) v. 1, no. Spring 1990 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Sparrow no. 59 1992 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- III. Sound Recordings
  - "Soundings;" National Humanities Center radio program; "An Evening of Poetry & Jazz: Dana Gioia & Ted Gioia" 1993, (2 cassettes) (Box 3, Folder 12)